So I am going to move on to a couple of other
things about more but Monte Carlo methods
which is actually not there in the book right,
so rather than we need to add the you see
trees paper to the model page right, bandit
based Monte Carlo planning, what is so amazing
about it, okay.
.
So there is a technique which people have
used people who typically talk about Monte
Carlo methods and you saw something called
row loads okay, so the idea behind roller
is the following so I have a heuristic way
of selecting actions I am trying to solve
the power problem they have some heuristic
way of selecting actions okay, so what do
I do is when I come to a particular state
right, so I use the heuristic right, and select
actions and then multiple trials from there,
right so I use whatever heuristic I have I
select run multiple trails so what is this
the heuristic you can think of it like a policy,
right.
Policy is what a mapping from states action
right I am not talking about value functions
or anything just a policy I use the policy
RN several trajectories like they just like
we talked about in the Monte Carlo case and
then what I do here is evaluate all the different
outcomes that came from running that particular
heuristic, right and then I pick the action
right that gives me the best possible expected
outcome.
If that did not make sense let us try it again,
okay if you have a deterministic heuristic
then what you should do is probably select
actions probabilistically at the beginning
and then run your heuristic okay so I start
from some state let us say I pick action a1
and then let us say I can pick action a2 there
are two actions that I can pick, let me heuristic
will suggest something well, let us say pick
action a1 first and then I run, I will policy
p and likewise pick action a2 run my policy
p okay, then I take the average value I get
here, so I take the average value I get here
then I take the action which ever gives me
the better average value, right.
So this might not be action given by p or
it might be action given by p we do not know,
right so all I am saying is given any policy
p I can do a roll out version of this, okay
what is it nice thing about doing this rollout
version I am guaranteeing you that whatever
policy you execute by virtue of doing roll
outs on p right, will be at least as good
as p and quite often better than p if a p
is not optimal right then this rollout execution
of the policy p will be better than p.
This rollout is this time generating multiple
trajectories using p right, it is like rolling
out the policies it is something like q(a)
right but this predates all of this thing
so this kind of roll out the idea of execution
right, this is nothing to do with the first
of all this is nothing to do with MDPs right,
so it could be any kind of games that you
are playing it could be adversarial setting
it could be anything right, I talk nothing
about value functions right, I talk nothing
about returns nothing is it predates all of
that okay.
This is in fact it is called rollout execution
of a policy okay, roller the execution could
the p could come from any heuristic right,
it did not have any notion of optimality associated
with it so what the roller the execution gives
you is whatever be the performance of p that
we had earlier I can better it if it is better
able, okay if I do not get a better policy
than that with a very high likelihood p is
optimal.
It why, think about it is very much like doing
one step of policy improvement then I have
done one step of policy improvement over p
if you think about it right so what did I
do here this is essentially an evaluation
of p like I did an evaluation of p specific
for starting from one step after s right,
so I just need a policy evaluation of p and
there was greedy with respect to that policy
evaluation so this is called rollout execution.
Yeah it is all a p till you reach the goal
state here. This depends, now I want to tell
me what it depends on.
UCT the least where the arms and you would
have from the root to the in each iteration
you mark from the root to the least that is
you are taking at one arm at each time step.
Yeah, and the each of the individual notes
you have that upper bound term there to maximize.
You are confusing to many things but they
are gone yeah so there was nothing good we
follow at one time still be follow one that
was 15 TVD still with you. Yeah. Using that
here we are following many.
Basically only one p but I am doing many territories.
Yeah, there it is holding one trajectory at
each time step we are following one. Yeah,
so we will come to that right I am not okay
I am not at talk to you about you trajectories
just ask me questions on what I have taught
you so far. This is not a history, this is
just rollouts so I am just talking to you
about rollouts I have not started talking
to you about trajectories okay, your question
was how many times should have run those trajectories.
Of course but how much anyway wants to tell
me what it depends on yeah, indirectly
exactly so closer so it depends on the variability
in the system, right. If this is deterministic
and p is deterministic one trajectory is enough,
right if the system is very stochastic you
know all kinds of random things are happening
then you probably need to run lot of trajectories
all if p itself is a very stochastic policy
you will have to run a lot of trajectories,
okay.
So it depends on the variability in this sampling
process if the variance in the samples you
draw is very small it is sufficient run a
small number of times, okay so any other factor
that will determine this trajectory length
why should trajectory length the determining
factor, in directly affects you know then
not about the variability trajectory length
can be a factor in another way computation
right, so how much computation time do you
have to spare between every decision is a
very practical consideration and you have
to actually be cognizant of it right.
So the length will affect the variability
but also affects amount of computation that
you have to do, so the longer the trajectories
are the fewer that you can generate. Ironically
the longer the trajectories are the more you
want to generate because it increases the
variability but you will have to do the opposite
so said any way of cutting down variability
here, exactly so do not go all the way to
the end right, stop somewhere in between depending
on how much time you have how much computation
you can spare for this and how much variability
is there in the system okay, so if you can
find a good heuristic that tells you how much
more it is going to cost if I run till the
end, right you can use that heuristic as a
terminal cost and remember when we talked
about why we call a value iteration dynamic
programming I said you can think of the value
as a terminal cost right.
So we have one step problem and then we have
a terminal cost like that here you will have
a many step problem and you will have a terminal
cost, right so what should be the terminal
cost or the natural terminal cost for us to
use it is a value function right, if you have
an estimate of the value function you can
use that as the terminal cost, see so far
I did not talk about the need for a value
function and I can do rollouts just given
a policy I do not need a value function but
the reason for me using a value function with
rollouts is if the trajectories are very long
the variability is very high, right.
So the longer vector is a case the smaller
the number of samples you can take refer it
is going to be very self defeating, because
the larger the variability you want to take
more samples so to kind of get around that
people started using estimates of value functions,
okay. So once you have value functions estimate
you can start doing something clever, okay
good. So this instead of apartment rollouts
was like a kind of a peripheral thing in the
RL community for a while right in fact when
I started teaching this course I used to give
a handout from a dynamic programming book
on load of rollouts because it was not covered
in the RL textbook so I used to take a Xerox
of well this was before every text book ever
printed became freely available on the internet
so I used to give a photocopy of the few pages
that discuss rollout policies right.
I gave it out to the class to read about rollout
policies and things like that and then things
change dramatically when I go I thought his
name was harder to pronounce well Chava and
another Hungarian with a hard to pronounce
name came up with something called upper confidence
trees UC trees, okay. so UC trees at the heart
use a rollout like idea right but we also
use the notion of value functions and upper
confidence bonds that we saw for bandits that
they use the notion of up UC upper conference
bound bandits UCB1 specifically they use the
idea from UCB1.
If you told you there are many variations
to UCB they use side is a very simple one
the UCB one and then married with them what
they call the Monte Carlo tree search, so
I am going to explain Monte Carlo tree search
first and then I will tell you what they did
to get UCTs and it turns out to be one of
the most powerful planning algorithms that
people use in the literature, okay. I should
explain what I meant by planning here because
it is very unique to Richchatin.
So Rich introduced this difference between
learning and planning into the community,
so learning is when you try to solve an MDP
without knowing any of the parameters well,
it is online that it is completely sample
driven and so on so forth. While planning
is when you have a some kind of specification
of a model right, and you use the model somehow
to solve their problem so all of these Monte
Carlo methods if you use a sample model.
Remember we talked about sample models and
full models right, so if you use a simulation
model or a sample model it comes under the
regime of planning because you are using a
model okay. So whatever we talked about can
either be planning our learning algorithm
depending on how you draw your samples, okay
if you draw your samples from the real system
then it becomes a learning algorithm if you
draw a samples from a simulation model then
it becomes a planning algorithm, right.
But there are other methods that use the model
more integrate a more integrally in their
method as opposed to whatever we have spoken
about so far, so there are many Monte Carlo
planning methods so we will talk about Monte
Carlo tree search. Let me see if I can might
what I really need to get my classes. The
will sorry hand it must be much worse than
usual today but let us put it down to variability
in the system. So you have to go and heat
the paper to get a better estimate so essentially
objective one subroutine of this right, so
this is a search function I am writing where
is a function called search, okay it is tarts
at some state and some depth at which it is
going to be called that right.
So I have some kind of a depth to which I
will search like some depth to which I will
search and I start by checking if this is
a terminal state, okay if it is double a state
I just returned a reward of 0 in the simple
case but i will return the terminal reward
so whatever is the terminal reward, right.
So in this case all the terminal rewards are
0 we are assuming that all the terminal rewards
are 0 otherwise I will return whatever is
the reward okay, and then I check if I have
reached my required depth right.
So if this say something is a leaf state that
means it is a state at which i will not do
any further processing right then I evaluate
whatever the state is whatever is the value
of the state I will return that value this
is like the terminal cost that we spoke about
it, if I stop here I leaves the value of such
state as the terminal cost right, so we will
evaluate that state somehow and will return
the value, okay. So what is next okay, now
it is not a lipstick okay, it is not a terminal
state so that means we have some assume so
we are not here we are not here so that means
you are somewhere here right,
So somewhere there what do I do is elect an
action right, so how do I select an action
sorry, based on the yeah, so heuristic function
so whatever was the original heuristic function
given to me, I will selected action based
on that heuristic function right, I will select
an action based on the heuristic function
then I will take one step I will simulate
the trajectory so this essentially what I'm
doing it I simulate the trajectory right,
I find what the next state is I also find
one is the reward I get for taking that action
okay. Well if you can actually behave in the
real world go ahead and behave in the real
world but how are you going to reset you back
to that thing and generate another trajectory
right, so if you want to do something like
this you better have a simulation model right,
so this is the whole idea behind rollouts
so you need to have a simulation model okay,
that is a point I missed or but you need to
have a simulation model can absorb obvious,
right.
When otherwise how am I going to generate
multiple trajectory starting from here, if
it is a real world then I have to roll my
robot back there and then say okay run again
okay, then catch it does not put it back there
and say run again and so on so forth that
is not going to work right, or imagine playing
games, right just like playing with a kid
right so the kid play some moves and say no,
no I want to take that back after four moves
so there will be like that right, anyway so
you do the next state and you get the reward
based on a simulation models.
And then what do you do you take your return
right, initialize it with the reward right
and then what do you do gamma times search
from the next stage essentially you are going
to face the entire path until you reach a
terminal state. Once you reach a terminal
state you keep popping back all the rewards
that you get not a terminal state once you
reach either a leaf state which means you
have reached the depth at which are going
to cut off or you reach the terminal state
at what you do at that point is you keep passing
the rewards back up the calling stack, right.
So this is like a recursive call I will keep
popping the reward back up so this summation
when it finally finishes computing will have
the return the complete return or the kind
of an adjusted return why I am saying adjusted
return because if i come to the stopping to
indicate condition here I will use some kind
of a value function estimator some evaluation
that I have so it is like a corrected return
or a truncated return.
So i will have that as my g right, and then
what they do I update the value of the state
and action, right I say this value of state
and this action you took and that is the total
return and they said depth at which the action
was taken from the state okay. So why is the
depth important here was it the first terminal
thing I would not even reach the right the
state is a terminal state I return 0 at the
very top I would not even reach the update
condition. Yeah, why do you how will the depth
give you how many states you move through
okay, and why do I need that so it turns out
that we are not even making any mark of hidden
assumptions here, so the so closer I am to
the end right so the value function will be
different right if I take if I have five more
steps to go or if I only take a scene 5 steps
I have a long longer direction to go right,
so I lead to maintain the distinction with
the value function right, I am still not come
to UC trees.
I told you about this right, so when we have
a fixed horizon when I say this event is going
to stop at time t=10 or something like that
right, so if you are one step away from that
you will behave in a different way, if you
100 steps away from that will behave in a
different way so I am just giving you the
number of steps that I have gone so that if
you want to specialize your value function
based on the number of steps that you have
taken you could do so, okay.
But there is another reason for carrying the
depth on but for the before we get to it okay,
before I talk about upper confidence bounds
and stuff like that so the Monte Carlo tree
search algorithm okay, we require you to carry
the depth run only for the diversion as you
can throw away the depth in the update, right.
So you need the depth here, so you can throw
in a depth in the update if you are assuming
everything is completely markup okay, yeah
it does not matter wherever you are in the
system right, so you do not need depth in
the case that is what I am saying even in
this.
Yeah, but only in the previous one you need
left leaf right, so this is fine so when you
call this you call it with your initial state
and the depth of 0 right, so here when you
call it you call it with the s and a depth
of 0 okay, and you could call this multiple
times from data, so every time you call it,
it will traverse one trajectory and it will
give you one return corresponding to that,
right. So every time you call this it will
give you a return corresponding to that and
then you can choose your best action based
on the returns that you are getting from that,
okay is it clear right.
So from here you will run this multiple times
right, now is take the returns again and again
and from there you choose your best action.
Other yeah, like I told you right, it depends
on how you choose the actions if your policy
has sufficient acceleration then you are fine
right, if you policy a sufficient exploration
you are fine that policy does not have sufficient
exploration then it becomes an issue right,
and how will each is the best action anyway
whichever next state gives you the maxi so
basically you will simulate each action once
okay, and then see which are the next states
you land up in which other next state gives
you the highest value you pick that action
we go okay, once or multiple times you can
always if you remember how you select actions
using the value function right, you have to
remember what we covered earlier so I said
how to recover a policy given a value function.
I given how to behave greedily with respect
to a value function not a Q function v function
so you could do that or you could modify this
whole thing to give you Q functions instead
of V functions highly modified is to give
you Q okay, so
this is this is a basic structure of what
is called as Monte Carlo tree search okay,
and depending on how you select actions which
you can get different kinds of algorithms
out of it and the most popular one is called
UC trees right.
Where the select action is going to use a
upper confidence bound like formulation so
I am going to look at the expected reward
for taking an action plus a term for the confidence
one right, so what is the term going to depend
on number of times you have pulled that arm
anything else Subha, yeah, so there is one
magic constant that comes in there okay, which
is what they needed to actually help them
prove some results okay, and they had one
son bound on that p constant.
Yeah, I forget what is it bound was remember
what the bond was yeah, so there is a bound
on that p constant essentially it is exactly
like you are all you see bandits right, the
expression will all be the same except that
instead of just having root of.
.
so it will 2 lnT by right, that used to be
the that is to be the constant that you add
right, so here what you do is instead of that
you have some magic constant CP times root
of ln T/n okay, so when you select action
so instead of selecting actions randomly or
I are going to fix p so what you do is you
look at the current estimated value function
for each action add CP root ln T/n okay, where
CP is a constant that is going to depend on
the problem that you are solving okay, so
the higher the variability in the system the
larger the CP has to be right.
Because you want to explore more right, higher
the variability in the system the larger the
CP will be okay this is something you typically
end up with determining empirically but there
is some bound on how large you have to search
and so on so forth right, I can get you that
numbers later. But you do this CP into root
ln T/n plus the q value right, and then you
select actions according to that and then
go back and pick your best action.
So what this is by U
so you have you have your explorer exploit
problem here right, so you need to explore
many different actions in this actual selection
space so that when we go back and select your
best action you have selected every action
offer enough right but you do not want to
keep exploring all the time because when you
go back you will not talk when you have wasted
too many sample suppose I give you like a
thousand samples that you can take you would
like to explore the more promising actions
more than the obviously hopeless actions so
if you do some kind of uniform acceleration
you are going to skip your budget too much
right across all of these things so doing
UCT like exploration gives you much more focused
learning right so just like we have in the
UCT case this gives you much more focused
learning okay, and this is one very elegant
way of converting a bandage solution for solving
the full RL problem right. Only to carry of
car is you need a simulation model you need
a simulation model to be able to do this right,
if you have a simulation bowl you can do UCT
style planning and turns out that in many
cases you can come up with some kind of a
rough simulation model, okay.
And you can get away with it and so it turns
out now it's become one of the very popular
solution methods and in many robotic situation
where you have a simulator it turns out to
be a very, very robust planning algorithm
right, and a lot of robotics now like to use
UC threes in their process okay any questions
on this so we will be putting up the paper
for you to read I will not say that the paper
is easy to read okay so most of where unlike
his lectures most of Chavez writings are very
hard to penetrate so how many of you watch
Chavez lecture.
One, linear bandits I told you to go to see
a video on linear bandits right its links
on the Moodle page not sure it's in Moodle
all the recharge our lectures are there is
it okay, so those are the three classes that
Java took right so you should see it not enough
to just see the link rather watch the video
so many people are telling me three links
are there and when I asked have you seen the
video only one hand goes up did you see the
video of Chavez you are not herein the RA
all happened you did not understand anything
okay.
You were here when they will trap happened
here you are going to say something, you have
live demo hopefully you will understand a
lot more now and the pleased to see that so
any questions on this you see threes yeah,
if you can come up with the parameter is representation
for the value function okay, that is well
behaved in the action dimension then it will
work so we will come to that aspect of it
later in the thing where I talked about using
this kind of parameter is representations
which since you asked.
I am telling it will work if you have a parameter
is representation so when you do this update
value right, so essentially that update our
actual set of parameters that represent the
function just like we talked about in reinforce
right, where we update the policy parameters
you need the value function parameterized
like that then you can get it to work and
give it more conditions on the well-behaved
nests of the value function.
Oh, in the continued action space is a good
question so let us think about that so that
is the thing I have right, so this N is essentially
the number of times I have basically taken
action so that is basically my depth kind
of thing and oh, yeah n is your depth so that
is the reason you need to pass depth everywhere
right and ln T is the number of times you
have taken that action.
Total number of yeah that is what it is right
the depth will be the total number of pulls
yeah, now T is the number of times have taken
that particular action right, so there is
that you be n is the number of times I have
taken that you sorry, sorry T is the total
so T will be the depth is I have to keep track
of n how many times have taken the action
so far right, so one possibility is to say
that I am going to do this in a parameter
explosion but glad to see whether that will
work or not right.
So yeah so without the exploration bonus this
will work in the country action space for
this we will have to figure out how to make
it work okay fine, all set okay we can move
on to the next topic
so this is end of chapter five so starting
chapter six but chapter five in the second
edition of the book has one additional section
okay so where they talk about some of the
recent work primarily being done by with certain
and his group on I'm trying to reduce variance
in Monte Carlo sampling right.
So one thing which they talk about is when
you really have long trajectories right, but
you have a small discount factor I say gamma
is like point three or something so the contribution
in the return of the subsequent terms is going
to die down very quickly right so you really
do not need to maintain this full product
that you could get away with doing something
that is truncated right I am looking at the
Pxi/Qxi right I do not have to do the whole
product I can do something truncated.
So how do you do that in a principled manner
and give some kind of guarantees about convergence
and stuff like that the he gives a very, very
high level quick discussion about that in
the last section in the chapter in the book
right, so again you can read it for information
that means I will ask questions on it in the
exam is what it means if you want to know
what it translates to but there are other
things you say ask you to rate which I did
not say our for information so those are fair
game.